so hi there my name is Joe Brewer and
I'm the research director here at the
rules and today I'm really excited to do
a short interview with Martin crook who
I'll introduce in a moment who also
works at the rules and for those of you
who have been following our work
recently you'll know that we are
currently involved in a campaign that is
critical of the sustainable development
goals and trying to get at the root
issues that look at the underlying
causes of poverty and inequality and one
of the things that we have realized
while running this campaign and in other
campaigns in the past is that the way
that we go about this work prompts
people to tell us their personal stories
about how they relate to the work that's
happening in development and that
sometimes those stories are quite
powerful just at a personal level they
really influence us and they bring us
inspiration and insight so we realized
for this campaign that we wanted to
highlight some of those stories and so
this video's is going to be online
accompanying a set of blog posts written
by people within the development sector
telling their personal stories and we
have right here in our midst a person
who has worked extensively in the
development sector and that has gone
through a process of radicalization or
changing from the norms of what people
typically do there and that is our
colleague here Martin and I think that
his story might be enlightening for
others so we're recording this interview
so maybe to get started Martin could you
just say who you are what is your role
at the rules and and then we'll go from
there sure I saw I'm not some kind so I
coordinated strategy for the rules and I
worked with Joe and our other colleagues
and one of the things that I think may
be helpful for setting some context here
for the viewers is too if you could tell
us how did you get into work on
development and poverty in the first
place you know what was the initial
feeling the passion that thing that got
you started what was that like for you
when you were younger yes I started
doing international drug will work but
professionally
15 years ago and it was an absolute
thrill I've always wanted to work in
this field it was like a natural
placement to gravitate towards and I was
thrilled when I got my first job in a
big NGO a big international aid agency
and I had an absolute blast and I look
back at that time with a lot of fondness
so it felt like I was doing something
that touched my soul that that was in
line with the purpose that I that I feel
I have in the world that's an
interesting thing about the work we do
here at the rules that we often take
this almost a contrarian position where
we're actively external to the
development sector in critical of it so
that might prompt in people's minds this
question if you were so happy working
for big NGOs you know like Save the
Children and Oxfam a-- what would what
was that process like for you to realize
that maybe what you were doing wasn't
all rosy and sunshine and you know were
the first indicators that maybe being
involved inside of those organizations
and inside the sector itself that maybe
you might be complicit in some problems
you know what were what were you
noticing there that first made you
uncomfortable my first discomfort really
starts to come when I look to public
attitudes of why people believe what
they do about poverty and inequality and
it became very apparent relatively
quickly when he starts to look at the
science behind people's attitudes
behaviors that they were locked in with
bias by a certain number of or a small
number of essential stories that have
talked about global poverty and
inequality particularly by those voices
that speak the loudest the big NGOs the
UN the World Bank and the very first one
of those stories that start to fall
apart for me was the story about charity
and the idea that the best response to
global or believe the legitimate
response to global poverty is for rich
people to give a little bit of money to
poor people and now I know that the big
and you know that not all they say but
that is one of the essential story that
underpins their corporate proposition to
the world and what I started to question
that
let's go down the rabbit hole and the
other story started to unravel for me
and that eventually led me out of the
NGOs to set up the rules so what was it
specifically about charity that you
found so problematic maybe could you
unpack that a little bit more where
there are specific assumptions or
beliefs that contradict your values or
their deficit well with you what were
those yes that's exactly what it was Joe
it was a sense that charity propagates
this idea that there is a moral order
into the world and that poor people need
to get more like rich people and there
is a moral equivalence made with virtue
being acquainted with wealth and poverty
being acquainted with a lack of virtue
now plenty of people in NGOs absolutely
do not believe that but when we started
to deconstruct the language in the
imagery in the stories are they were
telling what we found from a range of
sources was that is actually exactly the
story that they are telling because they
are so hooked on the charity story and
bear looked on the charity story because
they are from the charity business one
and when I started to realize that I
started that you know the big divergence
started to happen and I my own balance
and my own understanding of how the
world worked made it more and more
uncomfortable for me to be sitting
within that story and propagating being
a part of an industry that propagated
that story so over time I became more
and more uncomfortable and I found
myself feeling war a war against the
tide and eventually I was lucky enough
to be given the opportunity to follow
those values and the opportunity to help
set up the rules so I was very lucky but
it wasn't a very possible process for
quite no I imagine it wasn't uh this is
actually something I think it's at the
crux of the other personal stories that
will be shared online that accompany
this video there are people currently
working with in the development sector
who have similar dissonance between how
they feel about the work and the work
they feel they need to do and so I'm
curious if you could share what was it
like for you as you were
working within like let's let's take at
the time when I met you when you were
working at oxfam and we started
deconstructing the language together
this was about six years ago and then
the rules was formed about three years
ago so there was this intervening period
of several years where you had a growing
discomfort but you were still there so
what was that like for you to be him now
tonight because we were covering we were
asking questions and recovering
realities truths that I thought would be
liberating because I felt liberating to
me I was like oh that's why I've been
feeling so uncomfortable ok now I have
some empirical well-documented pretty
uncontroversial uncontroversial kind of
scientific evidence to explain to me why
I've been feeling uncomfortable so I
felt elated at first and over time I
started to have these conversations more
war within the sector and within other
agencies and gradually I started become
aware of the reality that these huge
organizations cannot accept these truths
very easily it's not that the people
inside and don't believe them it's not
even that there isn't an intent to move
beyond some of these things is that
these are huge complex organizations
complex adaptive systems in a way and
they can't just turn on a sixpence they
can't just change their direction like
this but where my discomfort really
reached a peak was when I started to see
people rejecting the logic and the
science because it provided too much of
a challenge water so I didn't mind that
it was going to take a long time what I
minded that people didn't seem to be
willing to rise to the challenge and it
was at that point that i came across
colleagues who helped me set up the
walls and so i can bring the sigh of
relief and i could follow my own truths
rather stay locked in the system that i
felt profoundly compromised I wouldn't
this I think gets right at the crux of
what's happening now with the
sustainable development goals because
you know 15 years ago the millennium
development goals were formed and
they've had a profound influence on the
trajectory of our planetary scale
economic
systems and political systems and here
we are doing something of a reset where
we are locking ourselves into or
potentially locking ourselves into a way
of conceptualizing economic development
for another 15 years and the current
state of the world you know I think of
my own background in atmospheric science
where we don't deal with the issue is
causing global warming in the next 15
years the consequences will be very dire
indeed so this is a time of rather
significant consequences and so many
people are operating within the paradigm
that has been established by sustainable
development goals and here we are
actively critiquing them making some of
our colleagues uncomfortable and and so
I'm wondering for the young people out
there today who are really excited and
passionate about changing the world and
they're coming into this moment and
these are some of the things that are
happening this moment what kind of
advice would you give to those people as
they uncover their own uncomfortable
truths what would you say to them from
your place you know where you on the
journey now yeah I'd say first of all
don't take change in the world keep you
on your own shoulders or your changing
your own organizations if you're
starting to feel uncomfortable with it
that passion you have is your greatest
weapon so hold on to that you don't need
to agree with everybody all of the time
in order to be make it stepping powerful
in your journey of uncovering the way
the world works and improving your
knowledge on that so so be patient with
yourself be patient with others and if
you do feel uncomfortable in your in
your organization's or in your job or or
with the big development story that's a
sign of health that's a good thing it
might feel bad in the moment because
that's what social norms do to us when
we start the challenge of a question one
of the things one of their powers is to
make us feel personally uncomfortable so
it's just important to make sure that
that you understand that discomfort in
the right way that it doesn't even by
examining the social norm but if you are
following we own your own true to your
own journey of inquiry and exploration
with integrity then
that is the most important thing you can
do it and these feelings of discomfort
or passing out so stick with it find
other people who are having the same
sort of questions that you are how I got
the people at the room because there are
lots of us around in and around a circle
/ also feel the same way I know that
there are lots and lots of other people
an increasing number of people out there
in the world who out on them saying that
save this comfort and even five years
ago 10 years ago get one so many
alternative places you could find it
good you could have these conversations
about that these feelings you have there
are more more of those places now so
find them joined up with like-minded
photos and you'll be fine so I guess the
basic takeaway here is really trust your
intuition seek truth even when it's
uncomfortable and for those people out
there in the world engaged in this
struggle with us realize you're not
alone and in today's world of digital
media as this video is a great example
we can find each other and we can share
our stories with each other and that in
itself is part of the solution so Martin
thank you so much for taking the time
with this interview it's really a
pleasure honor for me to to be your to
be able to call you one of my friends to
work with you on this and thank you for
sharing your story which I hope well in
both and others to go further along
their own spiritual path of growth and n
discovery so I thank you very much
Martin